<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation]]></title>
    <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2022-04-28T09:50:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Roundup &amp;#35;1]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2022/04/28/php-roundup-1/"/>
            <updated>2022-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2022/04/28/php-roundup-1/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the first <em>PHP Roundup</em>, where we’ll make regular updates on the improvements made to PHP by the <em>PHP Foundation</em> and other contributors. PHP Roundup is prepared by Ayesh Karunaratne from <strong><a href="https://php.watch">PHP.Watch</a></strong>, a source for PHP news and articles on upcoming changes.</p>

<p>In this series, we highlight some of the interesting and major improvements made to the PHP language. Traditionally, the PHP team releases a new minor version of the interpreter towards the end of each year, but the changes and improvements are discussed and implemented throughout the year.</p>

<p>You don’t necessarily have to be a PHP Foundation backer to follow the PHP Roundup. We’ll be publishing the posts on our website, and you can subscribe to a newsletter:</p>

<form method="POST" action="https://php-foundation-mailcoach.com/subscribe/9be4e2bd-f9d8-475c-b00e-2dcc4cf90056" class="mb-8 flex justify-center items-center h-screen">
    <div>
        <label for="email" >Email</label>
        <input type=email name="email" class="form-inp">
        <button type="submit" class="form-btn">Subscribe</button>
    </div>
</form>

<p>The PHP Foundation currently supports six part-time PHP contributors who work on both maintenance and new features for PHP. Maintenance is not limited to fixing bugs, but also includes work to reduce technical debt, making life easier for everyone working on PHP. The contributors funded by the PHP Foundation collaborate with other contributors on code, documentation, and discussions.</p>

<p>Things marked with 💜 are done by the PHP Foundation team.</p>

<p>Let’s get straight to the updates.</p>

<h2 id="rfc-updates">RFC Updates</h2>

<p>Every major change to PHP is discussed and implemented with the consensus of the PHP community. Each RFC proposes a set of changes, and the PHP Internals community holds a vote that lasts two weeks by default.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Accepted: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/null-false-standalone-types">Allow null and false as stand-alone types</a> 💜</strong></p>

<p>RFC by George Peter Banyard was accepted unanimously with all 38 votes in favor and is now merged into PHP.</p>

<p>Prior to this change, <code>null</code>and <code>false</code>could only be used as part of a Union Type, but not as stand-alone types. This change further improves PHP’s type system to be more expressive and defensive. See the <code>true</code> type RFC below that proposes adding <code>true</code>as a type too.</p>

<p>Learn more about this RFC from the <a href="https://phpinternals.news/99">PHP Internals News podcast</a> hosted by Derick Rethans.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Implemented: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/redact_parameters_in_back_traces">Redacting parameters in back traces</a></strong></p>

<p>RFC by Tim Düsterhus, approved with 24:1 votes in favor, is now implemented in PHP core.</p>

<p>This RFC proposed adding a <code>#[SensitiveParameter]</code> attribute that redacts the parameter's actual value when it is spewed out in stack traces and <code>var_dump</code>output. The attribute can be used to prevent leaking sensitive information in debugging logs.</p>

<p>Learn more about this RFC from the <a href="https://phpinternals.news/97">PHP Internals News podcast</a> hosted by Derick Rethans.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Discussion: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/true-type">Add true type</a> 💜</strong></p>

<p>RFC by George Peter Banyard is currently under discussion, to add true as a type to PHP. In PHP 8.0 Union Types, we added <code>false</code>as one of the possible members of Union Types, but left out <code>true</code>. This RFC proposes to complete it by adding <code>true</code>as a type as well.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Accepted: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/undefined_variable_error_promotion">Undefined Variable Error Promotion</a></strong></p>

<p>RFC by Mark Randall accepted with 33:8 votes in favor.</p>

<p>This proposes to convert the current behavior of PHP raising a warning for accessing an undefined variable (PHP 8.0+) to throw an Error exception instead in PHP 9.0.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Voting: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/undefined_property_error_promotion">Undefined Property Error Promotion</a></strong></p>

<p>Another RFC by Mark Randall proposes to throw an error on undefined class property access, similar to the now accepted changes with undefined variables. Notably, PHP 8.2 already emits deprecation notices on dynamic property creation (<a href="https://php.watch/versions/8.2/dynamic-properties-deprecated#exempt">with a few exceptions</a>).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Voting: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/readonly_classes">Readonly classes</a> 💜</strong></p>

<p>RFC by Máté Kocsis proposes to add support for readonly classes. In such a class, all properties are <code>readonly</code>and dynamic properties are forbidden. Voting is scheduled to start on April 27th.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Accepted: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecate_dollar_brace_string_interpolation">Deprecate ${} string interpolation</a> 💜</strong></p>

<p>RFC by Ilija Tovilo accepted with 31:1 votes in favor.</p>

<p>This RFC proposes to deprecate <code>"${foo}"</code> and "<code>${(foo)}</code>" string interpolation patterns. It does <em>not</em> deprecate the standard "<code>{$foo}</code>" pattern.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Accepted: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/remove_utf8_decode_and_utf8_encode">Deprecate and Remove utf8_encode and utf8_decode</a></strong></p>

<p>Learn more about this RFC from the <a href="https://phpinternals.news/98">PHP Internals News podcast</a> hosted by Derick Rethans.</p></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="merged-prs-and-commits">Merged PRs and Commits</h2>

<p>Some of the minor changes made to PHP are first made as a pull request to the <a href="github.com/php/php-src">PHP GitHub project</a>, and if deemed acceptable by PHP core maintainers, they are merged without going through a formal RFC process. We have automatic tests in place to flag PRs that break existing functionality. The majority of the minor changes from the community are made through PRs.</p>

<ul>
<li>New: <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/7823">Introduce CURLOPT_XFERINFOFUNCTION</a> by <a href="https://github.com/devnexen">David CARLIER</a>.</li>
<li>Fixed: <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/8133">Constants in Enum classes causes php-fpm worker to segfault</a> by Ilija Tovilo. 💜</li>
<li>Fixed: <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/8273">SplFileObject: key() returns wrong value</a> by George Peter Banyard. <strong>💜</strong></li>
<li>Fixed: Bug #<a href="https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=76003">76003</a> <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/33bb201b3eddbda0cc93c9cd1cb9adb4c77d0df2">FPM /status reports wrong number of active processes</a> by Jakub Zelenka <strong>💜</strong></li>
<li>Fixed: Bug #<a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/d8612fb6b7496a4f17e8250037a00b26623c1c77">77023 PHP-FPM cannot shutdown processes</a> by Jakub Zelenka <strong>💜</strong></li>
<li>Reviewed and merged various fixes and improvements to FPM by Jakub Zelenka: <strong>💜</strong>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/2874e5fa052d54affd31ed5eaf3e0d53c9116c93">Emitting error for invalid listen port</a> (implemented by David Carlier)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/7bb2a9ff38b739d2143134b6ce0d9cc3dd9b78fe">SELinux dumpable</a> (implemented by David Carlier)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/2f0918c638cbba0f5d36b9b2f3d0aa8cf95651c9">Clang warning in socket cleanup</a> (implemented by David Carlier)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/7be195caa7589560d5e1a019e389850fdb5c8a1e">Listening queue MacOS support</a> (implemented by David Carlier)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/1e562683cb995b9903f4d24ba9eb5bb89ae3fbfb">New default for listen backlog on Linux</a> (implemented by Cristian Rodríguez)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/ff90d42b8bc292bd7bfc532e29e5cdff242ee3e1">Kqueue typo in remove callback type</a> (implemented by David Carlier)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Fixed: Various (<a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/7752">1</a>, <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/8101">2</a>, <a href="https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=81660">3</a>) bugs related to DateTime support, as well as reimplementing serialization support for all classes, by Derick Rethans 💜</li>
<li>Improved: Migrated most of the CI setup from Azure Pipelines to GitHub Actions by Ilija Tovilo 💜</li>
<li>Fixed: <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/8310">Registry settings are no longer recognized</a> by Christoph M. Becker, reported by Vladimir S.</li>
<li>Several engine improvements by Dmitry Stogov and Nikita Popov.</li>
</ul>

<p>Apart from the highlighted changes above, there have been more improvements and fixes from @divinity76, Marco Pivetta, Arnaud Le Blanc, Alex Dowad, and more.</p>

<h2 id="mailing-list-discussions">Mailing List Discussions</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://externals.io/message/117577">Canonicalize "iterable" into "array|Traversable" and Reflection</a>, started by George Peter Banyard. 💜</li>
<li><a href="https://externals.io/message/117486">MySQLi Execute Query RFC</a>, started by Craig Francis.</li>
<li><a href="https://externals.io/message/117501">NULL Coercion Consistency</a>, also started by Craig Francis.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="support-php-foundation">Support PHP Foundation</h2>

<p>At PHP Foundation, we support, promote, and advance the PHP language. We financially support six part-time PHP core developers to contribute to the PHP project. You can help support PHP Foundation at <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation">OpenCollective</a>.</p>

<p>A big thanks to all our sponsors — PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>A special mention goes to <a href="https://mailcoach.app/">mailcoach.app</a> for providing us with a platform for the newsletter.</p>

<p>Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜️ 🐘</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>PHP Roundup is prepared by Ayesh Karunaratne from <strong><a href="https://php.watch">PHP.Watch</a></strong>, a source for PHP News, Articles, Upcoming Changes, and more.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Update, March 2022]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2022/03/31/the-php-foundation-update-march-2022/"/>
            <updated>2022-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2022/03/31/the-php-foundation-update-march-2022/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>We promised to publish monthly updates, but something everything went wrong in February.</p>

<p>Thank you all for being understanding about the lack of update in February. This post will bring you all up to date on everything that's been accomplished since our last post in January.</p>

<h3 id="php-foundation-core-developers">PHP Foundation Core Developers</h3>

<p>One of our primary goals for 2022 is to find and hire developers to work on the core.</p>

<p>We are excited to reveal our initial group of sponsored developers!</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Arnaud Le Blanc</strong> <a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">@arnaud-lb</a></li>
<li><strong>Derick Rethans</strong> <a href="https://github.com/derickr">@derickr</a></li>
<li><strong>George Peter Banyard</strong> <a href="https://github.com/Girgias">@Girgias</a></li>
<li><strong>Ilija Tovilo</strong> <a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">@iluuu1994</a></li>
<li><strong>Jakub Zelenka</strong> <a href="https://github.com/bukka">@bukka</a></li>
<li><strong>Máté Kocsis</strong> <a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">@kocsismate</a></li>
</ul>

<p>You might be surprised to see Derick Rethans’ name in the list above. After all, he was listed as a PHP Fellow when we announced the Foundation last year. Shortly after we launched the Foundation, Derick informed us of his desire to focus his work on developing and maintaining PHP's core and that he wanted to apply for sponsorship from the Foundation to make this happen. To avoid any conflicts of interest, Derick stepped down from his administrative role before he applied for sponsorship.</p>

<p>We are incredibly happy that these core developers have agreed to join the Foundation, and we are looking forward to the great things we can do together.</p>

<h3 id="code-of-conduct">Code of Conduct</h3>

<p>All participants of the PHP Foundation including administration members and developers are expected to abide by the <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.contributor-covenant.org%2Fversion%2F2%2F1%2Fcode_of_conduct%2F">Code of Conduct</a>.</p>

<p>To ensure enforcement of the Code of Conduct we are setting up a dedicated team. Tobias Nyholm <a href="https://github.com/Nyholm">@Nyholm</a>, who leads <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fsymfony.com%2Fcare">Symfony’s CARE team</a>, will be responsible for assembling and running the Foundation’s CoC team. Welcome aboard, Tobias!</p>

<h3 id="what%E2%80%99s-next">What’s next</h3>

<p>Our main goal for the next month is to set up a proper communication and development process. We will conduct several meetings to discuss technical and organizational matters.</p>

<p>Since the purpose of the Foundation is to train the next generation of internal developers, we want to emphasize maintenance and user-focused features to maximize our impact. As such, we will review the efforts and ensure the plans fall in line with such an agenda.</p>

<p>We would also like to reduce the bus factor of PHP. So whenever possible, developers will be expected to update the <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.phpinternalsbook.com%2F">PHP Internals Book</a> to ensure that no knowledge is lost.</p>

<p>On the administration side, we plan to work on increasing the transparency of our operations: to shed some light on the governance structure, discussions, and so on.</p>

<h3 id="php-foundation-stands-with-ukraine-%F0%9F%87%BA%F0%9F%87%A6">PHP Foundation stands with Ukraine 🇺🇦</h3>

<p>On February 24th, 2022, Vladimir Putin's Regime began an illegal war of aggression in Ukraine. There are no words to truly express our outrage at such disregard for human life.</p>

<p>Many PHP developers have lived in or are living in Ukraine, and the PHP Foundation is supported by many backers from Ukraine, including sponsors <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Foroinc.com%2Flets-stop-the-war-together%2F">Oro, Inc.</a> and <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fmacpaw.com%2F">MacPaw</a>.</p>

<p>If you, like many in the PHP Foundation, are desperate to find a way to help, there are some organizations listed below that are working to provide humanitarian aid to people who are caught up in this war.</p>

<p>We are proud that many of our sponsors stand with Ukraine too. Here are just a few examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fsymfony.com%2Fblog%2Fsymfony-stands-with-ukraine">Symfony</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.acquia.com%2Fblog%2Facquia-stands-ukraine">Acquia</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fblog.jetbrains.com%2Fblog%2F2022%2F03%2F11%2Fjetbrains-statement-on-ukraine%2F">JetBrains</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwordpress.org%2Fnews%2F2022%2F03%2Fepisode-26-matt-mullenweg-on-ukraine-community-and-wordpress%2F">Automattic</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/composer/packagist/commit/86244a3695fcaaac9c5ba4257a4314eae1c6d981">Composer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/Livesport_eu/status/1496925425821491208">Livesport.eu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.shopware.com%2Fen%2Fshopware-and-its-two-founders-support-caritas-international-aid-for-ukraine%2F">Shopware</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Please consider supporting the people of Ukraine. You can find more information on how to do so on the <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fen.isupportukraine.eu%2F">I Support Ukraine</a> website.</p>

<p>If you’d like to make a donation, consider <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.unicefusa.org%2Fwar-ukraine">UNICEF</a>, <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.peopleinneed.net%2Fdonate%2Fonce%3Famount%3D1000%26accountId%3D7">People in Need</a>, or any <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.globalcitizen.org%2Fen%2Fcontent%2Fways-to-help-ukraine-conflict%2F">other humanitarian organization</a> of your choice helping the people not only in Ukraine.</p>

<p>If you are a PHP developer in need of support, reach out to us at social@thephp.foundation and we’ll do everything we can to help you.</p>

<h3 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h3>

<p>Lots of you have kindly donated to the PHP Foundation, and we are extremely grateful!</p>

<p>We’d like to say a massive thanks to the following newly joined major sponsors for their very generous contributions:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fpaycomonline.com%2F">Paycom</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ec-cube.net%2F">EC-CUBE</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cambiumlearning.com%2F">Cambium Learning, Inc.</a> (<a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.learninga-z.com%2F">Learning A-Z</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>And shout-out to everyone else who has contributed, we are truly grateful to you all – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>A special mention goes to <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2F1password.com%2F">1password</a> for <a href="https://github.com/1Password/1password-teams-open-source#the-php-foundation">providing us</a> with a free membership to ensure all of our sensitive data is stored and shared securely.</p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💙💛 ☮️ 🐘</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Update, January 2022]]></title>
            <link href="/blog/2022/01/21/the-php-foundation-update-january-2022/"/>
            <updated>2022-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/blog/2022/01/21/the-php-foundation-update-january-2022/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>In November, the PHP Foundation was launched publicly and we’ve seen enormous support from the community.
Thanks to all of you who have already supported the initiative! We’re planning to update you about our workstream activities on a monthly basis, and this is our first update post.
Let’s take a look at what we’ve been working on!</p>

<h3 id="the-first-round-of-applications-is-now-closed">The first round of applications is now closed</h3>

<p>Since November, many developers have applied for sponsorship, and there were quite a few that we would be very happy to sponsor.</p>

<p>We are discussing the details with applicants and planning the budget.
In order to organize this correctly we need proper documents and agreements.
The JetBrains legal department and OpenCollective staff are helping us to prepare the required paperwork.</p>

<p>We plan to complete the preparations and sign the necessary documents in January.
After that, we will announce the list of the first batch of sponsored developers.</p>

<h3 id="how-we%E2%80%99re-making-decisions">How we’re making decisions</h3>

<p>So far, we have held three administration meetings where we discussed the pressing issues.
Each meeting and the decision-making process are documented in our organization on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/thephpf">github.com/thephpf</a>.
For now the details are hidden, but we would like to make these meetings and notes public at some point.</p>

<p>In the next few months, we plan to hold biweekly meetings and work on the foundation’s governance, rules, and bylaws.</p>

<h3 id="shout-out-to-our-sponsors">Shout out to our sponsors</h3>

<p>Many thanks to everyone who has donated to the PHP Foundation!</p>

<p>In addition to the founding sponsors – <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com">JetBrains</a>, <a href="https://automattic.com">Automattic</a>, <a href="https://www.acquia.com">Acquia</a>, <a href="https://www.zend.com">Zend</a>, <a href="https://craftcms.com">Craft CMS</a>, <a href="https://laravel.com">Laravel</a>, <a href="https://symfony.com">Symfony</a>, <a href="https://tideways.com">Tideways</a>, <a href="https://www.prestashop.com/en">PrestaShop</a>, and <a href="https://packagist.com">Private Packagist</a> – we have a whole new group of major sponsors!</p>

<p>A big thanks goes to the following companies who donated $10,000 or more:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.rakus.co.jp/">RAKUS</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.livesport.eu/">Livesport s.r.o.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://op.gg/">OP.GG</a></li>
<li><a href="https://polcode.com">Polcode</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.shopware.com">Shopware</a></li>
<li><a href="https://binc.jp">BASE, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://aternos.org">Aternos GmbH</a></li>
<li><a href="https://digitalscholar.org">Digital Scholar</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.ardennes-etape.be">Ardennes-étape</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Thank you to everyone else who has contributed – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/ThePHPF">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the foundation.</p>

<p>💖🐘</p>

<p>Feel free to contact us at <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact@thephp.foundation</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>